Martin Gold Collection 0012.002.008k
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
Martin Gold
1970-2000
0012.002.008k
Jewish Historical Society of Greater Hartford
2.0 Cubic feet 4 Boxes
Martin Gold, a member of the Jewish Community Relations Council and numberless other Jewish and civic organizations, devoted most of his life to the causes of religious freedom and human rights. Gold was an active local participant in the Anti-Defamation League, the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, the Jewish Community Relations Council and many other groups. His interests included Jewish-Black relations, the monitoring of hate groups, separation of church and state, and the security of the state of Israel. Gold amassed a large collection of material documenting his commitment to the causes he supported. After his death, these materials were donated to the JHSGH. The Martin Gold Collection opens a window on the aspirations and apprehensions of Connecticut Jews during the last few decades of the twentieth century. Of particular note are the records regarding anti-Semitic groups, the Nation of Islam, and the treatment of religion in the public schools. Most of the material in the collection is from the 1980s and 1990s. Martin Gold died in 1997.
Custodial History note
Provenance: the Jewish Federation gave this material to the JHSGH.
Gold, Martin; American Jewish Congress; Anti-Defamation League; Anti-Semitism; B'nai B'rith; Black-Jewish relations; Civil Rights; Connecticut Civil Liberties Union; Ethiopian Jews; Holocaust; Jewish Federation; Ku Klux Klan; Middle East; Nation of Islam; Soviet Jewry
- Series I: Martin Gold Archives: A
  - AIPAC, undated (Box 1)
  - American Jewish Committee, undated (Box 1)
  - American Jewish Congress, undated (Box 1)
  - Anti-Defamation League (ADL)/Connecticut Regional Office, 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 1)
  - Anti-Defamation League (ADL)/Connecticut Regional Office/Minutes and Meetings, 1990s, 1990-1999 (Box 1)
  - Anti-Defamation League (ADL)/Connecticut Regional Office/Miscellaneous, 1990s, 1990-1999 (Box 1)
  - Anti-Defamation League (ADL)/Connecticut Regional Office/Newspaper clippings and Press Releases, 1990s (Box 1)
  - Anti-Defamation League (ADL)/Connecticut Regional Office/Reports and Memos, 1990s, 1990-1999 (Box 1)
  - Anti-Defamation League (ADL)/General, undated (Box 1)
  - Anti-Semitism/Connecticut, 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 1)
  - Anti-Semitism/Connecticut, 1990s, 1990-1999 (Box 1)
- Series II: Martin Gold Archives: B-G
  - Baltic, Central, and East European Coalition, undated (Box 2)
  - Black-Jewish Relations/Connecticut, see also Nation of Islam, undated (Box 2)
  - Black-Jewish Relations/General, undated (Box 2)
  - Christian Jewish Relations, see also Interfaith, undated (Box 2)
  - Civil Rights, 1980s-1990s, 1980-1999 (Box 2)
  - Connecticut Association for Community Action, undated (Box 2)
  - Connecticut Civil Liberties Union, undated (Box 2)
  - Connecticut Fair Pay Campaign, undated (Box 2)
  - Ethiopian Jews, undated (Box 2)
- Series III: Martin Gold Archives: H-M
  - Hate Groups/Miscellaneous, undated (Box 3)
  - Hate Groups/Music, undated (Box 3)
  - Hate Groups/Internet, undated (Box 3)
  - Holocaust, 1980s-1990s, 1980-1999 (Box 3)
  - Human Rights, undated (Box 3)
  - Interfaith, undated (Box 3)
  - Jewish Labor Committee, undated (Box 3)
  - Ku Klux Klan, 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 3)
  - Ku Klux Klan, 1990s, 1990-1999 (Box 3)
  - Media, undated (Box 3)
  - Messianic Jews and Christian Evangelism of Jews, undated (Box 3)
  - Middle East, 1960s-1970s, 1960-1979 (Box 3)
  - Middle East, 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 3)
  - Middle East, 1990s, 1990-1999 (Box 3)
  - Middle East/Congressman Toby Moffet Controversy, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Militia Movement, undated (Box 3)
- Series IV: Martin Gold Archives: N-Z
  - Nation of Islam, 1980s, 1980-1989 (Box 4)
  - Nation of Islam, 1990s, 1990-1999 (Box 4)
  - New Jewish Agenda, undated (Box 4)
  - Regional Equity Network, undated (Box 4)
  - Religious Freedom/December dilemma, undated (Box 4)
  - Religious Freedom/General, undated (Box 4)
  - Religious Freedom/School Prayer, undated (Box 4)
  - Religious Freedom/Public display of religious symbols, undated (Box 4)
  - Religious Freedom/Schools/General, 2 folders, undated (Box 4)
  - Religious Right, undated (Box 4)
  - Skinheads, undated (Box 4)
  - Soviet Jewry, undated (Box 4)
  - World Affairs Council, undated (Box 4)